Register of the Nikolai Petrovich Kalugin Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Nikolai Petrovich Kalugin papers
1921-1999
2000C110
Hoover Institution Archives
3 microfilm reels (0.45 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, printed matter, personal documents, and photographs, relating to Russian émigré affairs, and especially to the Kharbinskii Politekhnicheskii Institut.
Kalugin, Nikolai Petrovich, 1902-1987
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
Nikolai Petrovich Kalugin was born in Khabarovsk on 17 February 1902. He graduated from the Kharbinskii Politekhnicheskii Institut as a civil engineer in 1924, and worked in that capacity for the Technical Department of the Chinese Eastern Railway until 1935. From 1935 to 1947, he headed his own engineering and contracting firm in Harbin, working on some of the larger construction projects in the city at that time. He also worked in the Philippines in this period. In 1941 he was elected president of the Society of Engineers in Manchuria, and from 1948-1953 lectured at the Kharbinskii Politekhnicheskii Institut.
Kalugin arrived in Brazil in 1954, working for Morrison Knudsen on the Itutinga Power Project, but ultimately received a visa for the United States (1958), where he remained until his death in San Francisco on 24 November 1987. He was devoted to his alma mater, the Harbin Polytechnic Institute, and collected many materials on it, including photographs and a run of the journal issued by its graduates abroad, Politekhnik, which also carried a number of articles written by Kalugin himself.
Chronology
1902 February 17 Born, Khabarovsk, Russia
1924 Graduated, Kharbinskii politekhnicheskii institut, Harbin, China
1925-1935 Civil engineer, Technical Department, Chinese Eastern Railway
1935-1947 Engineer and contractor, Harbin, China
1954 January 8 Arrived in Brazil
1987 November 24 Died, San Francisco, California
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of this collection deals with Russians in Manchuria and particularly Harbin in the 1920s-1940s. N. P. Kalugin was an engineer, and his papers contain significant information on the Russko-kitaiskii politekhnicheskii institut, later the Harbin Polytechnic Institute (Kharbinskii politekhnicheskii institut), including a complete run of the periodical Politekhnik, issued by its alumni association in Australia, and collected after his death by Kalugin's son, Nikolai.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Chinese Eastern Railway.; Kharbinskii politekhnicheskii institut.; China.; Engineers.; Railroads--China.; Russia.; Russians--China.; Russians--United States.; United States.
- Biographical File, 1921-1987 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Articles, curriculum vitae, death notices, educational, employment and medical records, and miscellany, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Speeches and Writings, 1959-1981 (Box 1)
  Articles, reviews and speech, arranged chronologically by title
- Subject File, 1930-1999 (Box 1-3)
  Diploma, printed matter and writings, arranged alphabetically by subject heading
- Photographs, 1921-1972 (Box 3)
  Album and one print, depicting mainly individuals and events associated with the Harbin Polytechnic Institute
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1921-1987 (Box 1)
  - Articles mentioning Kalugin (Folder 1: 1)
  - Curriculum vitae. (Folder 1: 2)
    Includes autobiographical notes
  - Death notices (Folder 1: 3)
  - Educational records (Folder 1: 4)
  - Employment records. (Folder 1: 5)
    Includes contracts, correspondence and letters of recommendation
  - Medical records (Folder 1: 6)
  - Miscellany (Folder 1: 7)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1959-1981
  General note
  See also SUBJECT FILE/Kharbinskii Politekhnicheskii Institut for printed copies of Kalugin's articles in the journal Politekhnik and additional articles not listed here
  - General. Reviews of Politekhnik, 1971-1981 (Folder 1: 8)
    Holographs and printed copies
  - Speech before a group of Harbin Polytechnic alumni in San Francisco on the occasion of the 37 th anniversary of the institute's founding, 1959 May 11 (Folder 1: 9)
    Holograph
  - "Iubileinaia data Kharbinskogo politekhnicheskogo instituta," Novaia zaria, 1970 October 28 (Folder 1: 10)
    Printed copy
  - "Pamiati professora P. S. Sviridova,"., [1971] (Folder 1: 11)
  - "75-letie Kitaiskoi Vostochnoi zheleznoi dorogi," Novaia zaria, 1972 January 21 (Folder 1: 12)
    Holograph and printed copy
  - "Nachal'noe razvitie goroda Kharbina," Novaia zaria, 1972 January 25 (Folder 1: 13)
  - "2-oe aprelia 1922 goda," Politekhnik, 1972 April 2 (Folder 1: 14)
  - "Piatidesiataia godovshchina osnovaniia Kharbinskogo politekhnicheskogo instituta," Russkaia zhizn', 1972 May 31 (Folder 1: 15)
  - "Semidesiatiletie Kitaisnoi Vostochnoi zheleznoi dorogi," Russkaia zhizn', 1972 August 18 (Folder 1: 16)
  - "Pamiati bol'shogo russkogo inzhenera Stepana Prokof'evicha Timoshenko," Russkaia zhizn', 1972 November 2 (Folder 1: 17)
    Holograph and printed copy. Includes background materials and slightly different version of article entitled "Pamiati zasluuzhennogo professora S. P. Timoshenko," Novaia zaria, 1972 June 13. Printed copy
  - Review of a concert performance by Irina Arkhipova, 1972 November 26 (Folder 1: 18)
    Holograph and advertisement
  - "Bokserskoe dvizhenie pri postroike KVzhd," Novaia zaria, 1973 March 17 (Folder 1: 19)
  - "Igor' Ivanovich Sikorskii," Politekhnik, 1973 April 2 (Folder 1: 20)
    Background materials and holograph (fragment)
  - "Krizis amerikanskogo inzhenera," Novaia zaria, 1973 April 26 (Folder 1: 21)
    Background materials and printed copy
  - "Moi kharbinskie gody," Politekhnik, 1974 April 2 (Folder 1: 22)
  - "Russkie inzhenery v SshA," Politekhnik, 1975 April 2 (Folder 1: 23)
    Background materials and holograph
  - "K 60-oi godovshchine osnovaniia Politekhnicheskogo instituta v gorode Kharbine," Russkaia zhizn', 1980 May 16 (Folder 1: 24)
    Holograph and typescript
- SUBJECT FILE, 1930-1999
  Diploma, notes and printed matter
  - Kharbinskii politekhnicheskii institut
    - General. (Folder 1: 25)
      Includes diploma of G. P. Kravetskii (relative of Kalugin), published historical overviews, and clippings about the institute
    - Den' Politekhnika, 1928 and 1930 (Folder 1: 26)
    - Izvestiia i trudy Russko-Kitaiskago politekhnicheskago instituta, #1 (1924) and 4 (1925) (Folder 1: 27)
    - Politekhnik
      - #1 (1969) - 9 (1978) (Box 2)
      - and jubilee issue, unnumbered (1982), #10 (1979) - 15 (1999) (Box 3)
  - Russians--China. (Folder 3: 1)
    Clippings, notes and writings related primarily to Russians in Harbin and the Chinese Eastern Railway
  - Miscellany (Folder 3: 2)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1921-1972 (Folder 3: 3)